[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "Electrophoresis is primarily used for the separation of which of the following in biological fluids?",
    "options": ["DNA", "RNA", "Proteins", "Lipoproteins"],
    "answer": ["Proteins"]
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "Who developed the first electrophoresis method for proteins in 1937?",
    "options": ["Watson and Crick", "Tiselius", "Mendel", "Franklin"],
    "answer": ["Tiselius"]
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "Which component of the electrophoretic setup controls the amount of electricity?",
    "options": ["Buffer", "Tank", "Power pack", "Support medium"],
    "answer": ["Power pack"]
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "Which of the following is commonly used as a support medium in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "Ethanol",
      "Cellulose acetate",
      "Sodium chloride",
      "Hydrochloric acid"
    ],
    "answer": ["Cellulose acetate"],
    "explanation": "Support medium in electrophoresis includes \n1. Cellulose acetate\n2. Polyarcrylamide gel\n3. starch gel or \n4. agarose gel"
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "What is the purpose of staining the cellulose acetate paper after electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "To visualize the proteins",
      "To remove excess buffer",
      "To increase the conductivity",
      "To reduce the pH"
    ],
    "answer": ["To visualize the proteins"]
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "One of the following dyes cannot be used for staining in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "Ponceau S",
      "Acetic acid",
      "Coomassie Brilliant Blue",
      "fat red"
    ],
    "answer": ["Acetic acid"],
    "explanation": "Stains in electrophoresis include\n1. Panceau S stain\nother dyes\n1. amido black\n2. coomasie brilliant blue\n3. sudan black\n4. fat red\n5. oil red\n6. malachite green"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "Which factor does not affect the migration and separation of solutes in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "Particle size and shape",
      "Net charge on the particles",
      "PH and ionic strength of the buffer",
      "Temperature of the buffer"
    ],
    "answer": ["Temperature of the buffer"],
    "explanation": "The migration and separation of solutes or colloidal particles in a mixture depends on :\ni)the intensity of the electric field\nii)particle size and shape\niii)net charge on the particles\niv)PH and ionic strength of the buffer\nv)type of support medium"
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "What is the isoelectric point (PI) of a molecule?",
    "options": [
      "The point at which the molecule has a net zero charge",
      "The point at which the molecule has a net positive charge",
      "The point at which the molecule has a net negative charge",
      "The point at which the molecule stops migrating in an electric field"
    ],
    "answer": ["The point at which the molecule has a net zero charge"]
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "At what pH is protein electrophoresis commonly performed?",
    "options": ["pH 4.6", "pH 9.6", "pH 8.6", "pH 10.2", "7.8"],
    "answer": ["pH 8.6"]
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "How does the ionic strength of the buffer affect electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "It decreases resolution",
      "It increases heat production",
      "It increases resolution",
      "It decreases migration velocity"
    ],
    "answer": ["It decreases migration velocity"]
  },
  {
    "id": 11,
    "question": "What is the purpose of the power pack in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "To control the amount of electricity",
      "To control the temperature",
      "To regulate the pH",
      "To monitor the progress of electrophoresis"
    ],
    "answer": ["To control the amount of electricity"]
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "question": "Which type of molecules have a net negative or positive charge at a given pH due to their amino acid composition?",
    "options": ["Proteins", "Lipids", "Carbohydrates", "Nucleic acids"],
    "answer": ["Proteins"]
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "question": "How many distinct groups are proteins separated into in an electrophoretogram?",
    "options": ["2", "3", "4", "5"],
    "answer": ["5"]
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "question": "What is the principle behind the migration and separation of solutes in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "Particle size only",
      "Net charge on the particles only",
      "PH and ionic strength of the buffer only",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["All of the above"]
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "question": "Low albumin band with beta and gamma globulin band bridging due to increase in gamma globulin band is seen in ?",
    "options": [
      "Liver cirrhosis",
      "Nephrotic syndrome",
      "Renal failure",
      "Cerebral oedema"
    ],
    "answer": ["Liver cirrhosis"],
    "explanation": "Some electrophoretic patterns:\n1. Nephrotic syndrome â€“ decreased albumin , alpha 1 and gamma globulin bands with increased alpha 2 and beta globulin bands due to increased alpha 2 macroglobulin\nA band may be visible at the point of application mimicking a momoclonal band\n2. liver cirrhosis (chronic liver disease)- low alb band with beta and gamma globulin band bridging due to increase in gamma globulin band"
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "question": "What is the role of the buffer in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "To increase the conductivity of the medium",
      "To provide a medium for the migration of charged particles",
      "To regulate the pH of the medium",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["All of the above"]
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "question": "How does the support medium contribute to the separation of solutes in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "It provides a medium for the migration of charged particles",
      "It affects the migration velocity of the particles",
      "It determines the PH of the buffer",
      "It does not play a role in separation"
    ],
    "answer": ["It affects the migration velocity of the particles"]
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "question": "Which component of the electrophoretic setup is responsible for producing sharper bands but also increases heat production?",
    "options": ["Buffer", "Tank", "Power pack", "Support medium"],
    "answer": ["Buffer"],
    "explanation": "The ionic strength of the buffer affects the current and migration velocity of the mols.\nHigh ionic strength buffers have the advantage of increasing resolution by producing sharper bands but have the disadvantage of increased heat pdtn."
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "question": "Which type of staining is commonly used to visualize proteins after electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "Ponceau S stain",
      "Coomassie Brilliant Blue stain",
      "Sudan Black stain",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["All of the above"]
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "question": "Which factor does not affect the migration and separation of solutes in electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "Type of support medium",
      "PH of the buffer",
      "Net charge on the particles",
      "Humidity levels"
    ],
    "answer": ["Humidity levels"]
  },
  {
    "id": 21,
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a type of electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "Isoelectric focusing",
      "Capillary",
      "Southern blotting",
      "Western blotting"
    ],
    "answer": ["Southern blotting"]
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "Which type of electrophoresis allows migration of solutes for a fixed time followed by visualization of the pattern of zones of the separated substances?",
    "options": [
      "Isoelectric focusing",
      "Capillary",
      "2-dimensional",
      "Zone electrophoresis"
    ],
    "answer": ["Zone electrophoresis"]
  },
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "Which of the following is a common clinical lab electrophoresis method?",
    "options": [
      "Capillary electrophoresis",
      "isoelectric focusing",
      "2-dimensional",
      "Zone electrophoresis"
    ],
    "answer": ["Zone electrophoresis"],
    "explanation": "The common clinical lab electrophoresis method is the ZONE electrophoresis"
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "Uses of zone electrophoresis in clinical labs include the following except?",
    "options": [
      "Separation of abnormal haemoglobin variants",
      "isoenzyme pattern analysis eg LDH, ALP, CK.",
      "Quantification of glycated haemoglobin fractions",
      "Separation of proteins into albumin, alpha 1 and 2, beta and gamma globulins"
    ],
    "answer": ["Separation of abnormal haemoglobin variants"],
    "explanation": "Uses of electrophoresis\n1. separation of proteins eg plasma proteins into albumin, alpha 1 and 2, beta and gamma globulins\n2. identification of abnormal haemoglobin variants (A,S,C)\n3. Quantification of glycated haemoglobin fractions\n4. isoenzyme pattern analysis eg LDH, ALP, CK.\n5. Separation of lipoproteins"
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a use of electrophoresis in clinical labs?",
    "options": [
      "Identification of abnormal haemoglobin variants",
      "Separation of DNA fragments",
      "Isoenzyme pattern analysis",
      "Separation of proteins into albumin, alpha 1 and 2, beta and gamma globulins"
    ],
    "answer": ["Separation of DNA fragments"]
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "Which condition is characterized by decreased albumin, alpha 1 and gamma globulin bands with increased alpha 2 and beta globulin bands due to increased alpha 2 macroglobulin?",
    "options": [
      "Nephrotic syndrome",
      "Liver cirrhosis",
      "Chronic liver disease",
      "Hemochromatosis"
    ],
    "answer": ["Nephrotic syndrome"]
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "What might be visible at the point of application in nephrotic syndrome, mimicking a monoclonal band?",
    "options": [
      "Alpha 1 globulin band",
      "Beta globulin band",
      "Gamma globulin band",
      "A band"
    ],
    "answer": ["Alpha 1 globulin band"]
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "In liver cirrhosis, what is the appearance of the albumin band in electrophoresis?",
    "options": ["High", "Low", "Bridging", "None of the above"],
    "answer": ["Low"]
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT an abnormal haemoglobin variant that can be identified using electrophoresis?",
    "options": ["A", "S", "C", "T"],
    "answer": ["T"]
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "What is the primary purpose of isoenzyme pattern analysis using electrophoresis?",
    "options": [
      "To identify DNA fragments",
      "To separate lipoproteins",
      "To quantify glycated hemoglobin fractions",
      "To analyze enzyme patterns such as LDH, ALP, CK"
    ],
    "answer": ["To analyze enzyme patterns such as LDH, ALP, CK"]
  }
]
